<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc ipr='trust200902' docName="draft-arkko-activity-json-00" category="info">

  <?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
  <?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes"?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Activity JSON">Activity JSON</title>

    <author initials="J" surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
      <organization>Planetskier</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Välitie 1B</street>
          <city>Kauniainen</city> <code>02700</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jari@arkko.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="May" year="2020" />

    <keyword>JSON</keyword>
    <keyword>Activity</keyword>
    <keyword>GeoJSON</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>Activity JSON is a simple format that allows providing
      information about activities and their geographic positions.  It
      is an extension of existing formats, specialized to provide some
      additional information that applications can use to perform
      filtering, showing useful information to the user, and so
      on. Activity JSON is primarily targeted towards passing
      information between a web server and an application running in a
      browser.</t>
      
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>The author has worked with web applications that deal with
      sports activities in different locations. The applications allow
      displaying varying activities on a map, smart filtering based
      on specific type or attributes of those activities.</t>

      <t>Activity JSON is a simple format that allows providing
      information about activities and their geographic positions.  It
      is an extension of existing formats, specialized to provide some
      additional information that applications can use to perform
      filtering, showing useful information to the user, and so
      on. Activity JSON is primarily targeted towards passing
      information between a web server and an application running in a
      browser.</t>

      <t>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) <xref target="RFC8259"/> is
      a popular format used in web applications. GeoJSON <xref
      target="RFC7946"/> <xref target="GeoJSON"/> is a format for
      encoding a variety of geographic data structures using JSON.</t>

      <t>Activity JSON has been used in building websites for
      skiing-related activities reported in <xref
      target="Planetskier"/> and caving-related activities reported in
      <xref target="Luolaseura"/> and <xref
      target="Planetcaver"/>.</t>

      <t>The rest of this document is organized as follows. <xref
      target="goals"/> discusses the goals for this work, and <xref
      target="modelling"/> covers some of the modelling issues. <xref
      target="gen2"/> describes the currently specified format for
      Activity JSON. The description includes specification of the
      syntax rules and the structure as inherited from base
      specifications, and a detailed discussion of the specific
      properties that can be described by Activity JSON objects.</t>

      <t>There are, however, two older versions of Activity JSON.
      Software libraries support all format variants, so using an
      older format is generally ok, but for new information the
      Generation 2 format is RECOMMENDED.  Note that with Generation 2
      format, Activity JSON can be directly supplied to a wide variety
      of software that accepts GeoJSON. The earlier format generations
      and compatibility discussion can be found in <xref
      target="gen1"/>, <xref target="gen0"/>, and <xref
      target="compat"/>.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Normative Language">
      
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
      target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="goals" title="Goals">

      <t>There are many tools and formats to manipulate, collect,
      store, and display collections of points or other geographic
      objects. Formats for information relating to this (such as <xref
      target="RFC7946"/> or <xref target="KML"/>) are prior art and
      not something that needs to be replicated.</t>

      <t>However, what is not as easily available in these formats is
      all the additional metadata associated with the entries. Such
      metadata is essential for many functions, like searching,
      filtering, organizing information in various ways, sorting, and
      so on. Of course, any particularly application can use whatever
      metadata it prefers to, but for some categories of applications
      it may be preferrable to provide a common definition of what
      information is needed. This will facilitate interoperability
      across systems, and enable easier sharing of data.</t>

      <t>The goal of this document is to define such metadata in a
      concrete fashion as an extension of GeoJSON properties, for
      sports/nature exploration type activites, such as skiing or
      caving. Specifically, we wish to define a data format for
      applications sharing information about activities, their
      locations, and associated metadata.</t>
      
      <t>It should also be noted that defining a data format
      is just about defining a data format, and it is not a solution
      for all other problems. For instance, the following are outside
      the scope of the sharing data format and therefore
      non-goals for this effort:

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Representing media about particular activities. This work
        takes the approach that all substantial information is merely
        a reference rather than the data itself.</t>
        <t>While this format is well suited for sharing information
        about
        detailed maps about the places of the activities -- such as
        ski area  maps or cave maps -- this happens again via
        references.
        Representing such complex maps themselves inside this format
        is not a goal, and the format does not have the expressive
        power for such specialized work. References are sufficient for
        our purposes.</t>
        <t>Databases -- how data is stored in servers and other
        systems is outside the scope of this work. Databases are often
        needed, but we take no position on how that happens, it is an
        internal matter to who ever is building the system in
        question.
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        One should note that database access mechanisms are often
        used to retrieve data, and as such, are an alternative to
        datasharing. However, we have found that binding to particular
        details of access via a database is often more complex than
        merely passing easily parsable JSON around. But there are of
        course situations where databases are necessary as well.
        The main goal of this work is to enable sharing in an
        easy, web-friendly manner, and support applications that might
        for instance fetch data from multiple sources.</t>
        <t>Access control to non-public information. This format is
        primarily designed for carrying information that is publicly
        available. It has support to hide some things -- such as the
        location of caves with restricted access -- but it is not a
        good vehicle for managing access for more information to specific authorized
        individuals. The format is best suited for bulk transfer of
        public data (with the occasional obfuscated location).</t>
        <t>Functionality of applications. What the various
        applications do with the information shared is outside the
        scope of this work.</t>
      </list></t>

      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="modelling" title="Modelling Activities">

      <t>First off, there's a philosophical question of whether we are
      describing real-world entities or their exploration. We've
      chosen to model everything as visits or exploration, leaving
      some coordinates, descriptions, articles and maps as a record of
      the activity. But this still describes real-world entities such
      as ski slopes or caves accurately. The information is just that
      -- information. Whether an application or human decides to pay
      attention to who visited that place and when or just the
      characteristics of the place, is their choice.</t>

      <t>Nevertheless, we've chosen to structure the model around the
      locations, in line with GeoJSON. Each activity, report,
      participant list, cave map, etc. is hanging off the location,
      rather than being an independent entity that has
      locations. We've found this design to be most workable for
      software that attempts to display activities on a map.</t>
      
      <t>There is an interesting design trade-off between describing
      high-level entities vs. going all the way to the finest
      detail. As noted above, we have chosen to not attempt to model
      detailed maps of particular ski resort, for instance. That is
      something reserved for the ski resort itself. Nevertheless,
      sometimes it is useful to not just describe that a ski resort
      exists at a particular location, but also describe visits or
      activity that takes place at a special place in that ski resort,
      e.g., a mountain top.</t>

      <t>In great amounts, such additional information can become
      confusing, however. We've chosen to enable the model to show
      relationships, such as a mountaintop having a relation to the
      ski resort. Or a side peak having a relationship to the main
      peak of a mountain. This additional information can then be
      chosen to be used or displayed by software or ignored, depending
      on the needs of the application, the granularity of the map
      being shown, etc.</t>
      
      <t>The distinction between a main attraction and side ones is perhaps more relevant for caving.
      Where there are caves there are often several in a group, or
      small side caves accompany a larger cave. And even for a large
      cave itself, there may be multiple entrances. While Activity
      JSON does not attempt to describe the internal maps of the cave
      (except by reference), it can still describe the fact that there
      are side caves and multiple entrances. This information can be
      useful when looking at an area of caves in detail.</t>

      <t>In this version of the specification, the supported
      activities and their sub-activities are as follows:
      
      <list style="hanging">
        
        <t hangText="Biking"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are Road and Mountain.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Canoeing"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Caving"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        
        The sub-activities consist of a number sub-attributes
        that can be combined to represent a detailed activity and
        environment. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        
        The sub-activities can represent the following 
        aspects. Different aspects can appear in an orthogonal
        manner, e.g., you could be diving while visiting an ice cave.
        Not all combinations make sense, of course, but in general one
        can combine a number of different sub-activities in one experience.
        
        <list style="hanging">
          
          <t hangText="Environment"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

          To describe the environment, use one of the following three
          sub-activity tags: Rock, Ice, Man-made, and Other-material. <vspace
          blankLines="1"/>
          
          There is an additional sub-sub-activity tag for Rock, to
          describe the kind of rock being explored: Rock-Granite,
          Rock-Limestone, Rock-Sandstone, Rock-Marble, Rock-Volcanic,
          and Rock-Other. <vspace blankLines="1"/>

          Another additional sub-sub-activity tag for the Rock
          sub-activity tag is how the caves were formed, i.e., their
          morphology: Morphology-Crack, Morphology-Boulders,
          Morphology-Karst, Morphology-Volcanic, Morphology-Erosion,
          Morphology-Weathering (e.g., Tafons), Morphology-Crystallization,
          and Morphology-Other.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          
          More than one of these may appear in a single cave. <vspace
          blankLines="1"/>

          Note that while several types of Man-made environments may
          exist, e.g., tunnels or bunkers. These should additionally
          be categories of Urban-exploration, and properly specified
          there. A single reading list item may cover multiple
          activities, so an activity list of
          ["Caving","Urban-exploration"] and sub-activity list of
          [["Man-made"],["Bunkers"]] is perfectly legal Activity JSON.</t>
          
          <t hangText="Caving method"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

          Caving can be performed in various ways. The following
          sub-activity tags can be used: None, Basic, SRT, Swimming, Boating,
          Diving, Digging, and Skiing. More than one of these may appear in a
          single trip. The tag None describes that no actual caving
          was done.</t>
          
          <t hangText="Associated activities"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

          Sometimes we report on activities related to, but not actual
          caving. This can be represented with the following
          sub-activities: Surveying, Researching, Training, Studying,
          Social, Equipment, Media, and Other.  For instance, Caving:Media
          can represent watching a caving-related movie and
          Caving:Equipment can represent a story about fixing a cave
          lamp.</t>
          
          <t hangText="Independent characteristics"><vspace
          blankLines="1"/>
          You may be visiting a show cave tour, if so, you can use the
          sub-activity tag "Showtour". Note that this describes a
          visit/article, not the cave itself, as one may be on a wild
          cave exploration even in a show cave.</t>
          
        </list>
        </t>
        
        <t hangText="Charity"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Climbing"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are Mountain, Rock, Ice, Wall, and Volcanoes.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Diving"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Equipment"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Hiking"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="History"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Sauna"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are Normal, Smoke, Steam.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Skiing"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The
        sub-activities are Outdoor, Indoor, Snow, Sand, Rock, Ash,
        Asphalt, Grass, Mud, Plastic, Other-substances, and
        Imported-snow.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Skydiving"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Sliding"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are the same as for Skiing.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Snowboarding"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are the same as for Skiing.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Surfing"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Swimming"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Indoor, Outdoor, Underground, Water, Ice, and Balls (as in
        children's "ball pit"). In addition, when the type is Water or
        Ice, the additional items Waterbody-River, Waterbody-Lake,
        Waterbody-Sandpit, Waterbody-Sea,
        Waterbody-Pool, Waterbody-Cave, and Waterbody-Other can be
        specified. The items Beach and Nature can also specified for
        official and unofficial swimming spots.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Travel"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Urban-exploration"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The sub-activities are Tunnels, Buildings, Ruins, Bunkers,
        Quarries, Industrial, Silos, Ski-lifts, Landfills, Castles,
        Vehicles, Trenches, Memorial, Historic-sites, Bridges,
        Skating-rinks, Amusement-parks, Airports, Catacombs, Railways,
        Smokestacks, Towers, Prisons, Harbours, and Military.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Wakeboarding"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Walking"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Waterfalls"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Meteorites"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
        <t hangText="Other"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        There are no sub-activities.</t>
        
      </list></t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="gen2" title="Generation 2 Format">

      <t>The format is a specialization of GeoJSON. Every Activity
      JSON object is also a valid GeoJSON object, but has some extra
      properties to carry the information that is needed to describe
      the activities.</t>

      <t>For example, an empty file contains just:</t>
      
      <figure>
        <artwork>
          {
            "type": "FeatureCollection",
            "features": []
          }
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <t>Here's an example of a file with just one entry:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
  {
    "type": "FeatureCollection",
    "features": [
        {
          "type":
             "Feature",
          "geometry":
             { "type": "Point",
               "coordinates": [60.30145486, 24.62792567] },
          "properties": {
            "n": "Kattilajärven iso lippaluola, Nuuksio, Espoo",
            "m": "https://example.com/cavemap-kattilajarvi.pdf",
            "l": 9.3,
            "la": "exact",
            "k": "Espoo",
            "c": "Finland",
            "o": "Europe",
            "rl": [{ "t": "Kattilajärvi roof caves",
                     "i": "https://example.com/a-picture.jpg",
                     "w": ["Jari"],
                     "y": 2020,
                     "m": 5,
                     "a": ["Caving"],
                     "sa": ["Rock"],
                     "u": "https://example.com/an-article.html" }
                  ]
           }
        }
    ]
  }
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <section anchor="usage" title="Features">
        
        <t>In this version of the specification, only features of the
        type "Point" are allowed.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="prop" title="Properties">

      <t>The properties described in a GeoJSON file are as follows:
      
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="n"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The name of the place. By convention the last item of the name
        (after last comma) should be city name. Mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="an"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        This optional field allows listing alternative names, should
        the place have several names or several alternative spellings
        of the same name. The value, if present, should be an array
        of strings in the same format as in the "n" field.</t>
        
        <t hangText="lat, lon"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The coordinates, in WGS84 format. Mandatory.</t>

        <t hangText="ac"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        In some cases there are alternative coordinates for some
        reason, perhaps different measurements or different entrances
        or different location within a larger entity. The "ac" field
        can be used to carry these coordinates. Its value should be an
        array of records, with each record having  the "lat" and "lon"
        fields. The "ac" field is optional.</t>

        <t hangText="d"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Free-form text 
        description of the location. Optional. Note that this SHOULD
        NOT be used to write long stories about the location, but
        rather a line or two about it. The articles and URLs
        referenced from the entry are the right place to write full
        descriptions. But the short description may be displayed by
        tools when hovering over the location by mouse, etc. <vspace blankLines="1"/>

        The text itself can be in two forms, either simply the text as
        is. In that case there is only one text available, and it is
        in whatever language it happens to be. An example:

      <figure>
        <artwork>
          "d": "This place is really cool!"
        </artwork>
      </figure>

        Alternatively, the
        text may be a record with two-letter language codes
        representing language versions. See <xref target="lc"/> for
        the available language code designations. <vspace blankLines="1"/>

        Here is an example:
        
      <figure>
        <artwork>
          "d": {
                   "en": "This place is really cool!", 
                   "fi": "Ei paskempi paikka!"
                 }
        </artwork>
      </figure>
        </t>
        
        <t hangText="ad"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Optional alternative
        descriptions, if any. The value should be an array of
        description objects, where each object should have the field
        "d"  for the description (as above) and "s" for  the source of
        the alternate description.</t>
        
        <t hangText="rn"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        This optional attribute enables building relations between
        different items. The "rn" attribute identifies another entity
        in the same dataset that there is a special relationship to.
        The value of the "rn" attribute should be a list, with one
        list element for each different relationship that the item
        is involved in. By default, items do not have relationships,
        and in this case the list can be empty or omitted entirely.
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        
        Each entry in the list should be a string, the name of the
        place where there's a relationship to, i.e., the value of the
        "n" attribute in some other item in the same dataset.
        The "rt" attribute provides the type of this relationship.</t>
        
        <t hangText="rt"><vspace blankLines="1"/> This optional
        attribute MUST be present when the "rn" attribute is
        present. The "rt" attribute describes the type of the
        relationship. Since there can be a number of relationships,
        the value should be a list. Each list item should be a string
        that describes a relationship type. Currently supported
        relationship types are:
        
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>"entranceof": This entity is another entrance to the
          same cave as described in the entity referred to.</t>
          <t>"entrance": A reverse relationship of the above, i.e.,
          this entity points to another entity that represents another
          entrance to this cave.</t>
          <t>"sidecaveof": This entity is another (side) cave of the
          main cave described in the entity referred to.</t>
          <t>"sidecave": A reverse relationship of the above, i.e.,
          this entity points to another entity is a side cave of this cave.</t>
          <t>"peakof": This entity is a mountain peak, top lift, or
          other similar location in the entity referred to.</t>
          <t>"peak": A reverse relationship of the above, i.e.,
          this entity points to another entity is a peak of this
          mountain or ski  area.</t>
          <t>"secondaryto": This entity is an alternate/secondary
          entity that describes something already described by some
          other entity. This can be used to represent reports from
          multiple, alternate sources about the same thing, for
          instance, when for some reason there is no desire to merge
          their entity descriptions in other ways.</t>
          <t>"secondary": A reverse relationship of the above, i.e.,
          this entity points to another entity that is a secondary entry
          for this entity.</t>
          <t>"partof": This entity is somehow otherwise part of the
          entity referred to.</t>
          <t>"part": A reverse relationship of the above, i.e.,
          this entity points to another entity that is a part of this entity.</t>
        </list>

        Implementation note: Implementations typically calculate
        the reverse relationships automatically from one side of the
        relationship. So, for instance, only the "sidecaveof"
        relationship needs to communicated in an Activity JSON file,
        and the receiver builds the "sidecave" relationships based on
        that.</t>

        <t hangText="alt"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        An optional attribute that describes the altitude the location
        or the highest point in the destination, in meters.</t>

        <t hangText="aa"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        An optional attribute that describes alternative altitudes (if
        there are several measurements or different locations within
        the place).</t>
        
        <t hangText="fz"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Set to true if the coordinates are "fuzzy" to hide the true
        location for privacy etc. reasons. Default is false. This
        attribute is optional.</t>
        
        <t hangText="m"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The cave map link URL, if any. If there's no URL, the
        attribute SHOULD NOT be specified at all (and SHOULD NOT be
        set to, e.g., empty string, although it is RECOMMENDED that
        software recognises empty strings similarly to missing
        attributes.</t>

        <t hangText="am"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        If there are several maps, additional links MAY be provided in
        this optional attribute. Its value should be an array of URL strings.
        </t>
        
        <t hangText="l"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The length of the cave in meters, if known. The attribute is
        optional, and should be left out if no value is known. The
        value should be a number and can include a decimal point.</t>
        
        <t hangText="lc"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        If the length is not specified, one can also specify a length
        category. This is expressed as a string of the forms "&lt;a",
        "&gt;a", or  "a&lt;&lt;b" where a and b are numbers that may include
        also decimal points. The numbers represents cave lengths in
        meters, and express the cave length size category, e.g., cave
        larger than 50 meters long would be represented as "&gt;50".</t>
        
        <t hangText="h"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The height/vertical difference in the cave in meters, if
        known. The attribute is optional, and should be left out if no
        value is known.</t>
        
        <t hangText="la"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The cave length and height accuracy ("exact" or "approx"). The
        attribute is optional, and the default value is "approx" if no
        other value is provided.</t>
        
        <t hangText="k"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The city/town/county. In Finland the relevant "kunta" or
        community should be filled in. This attribute is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="c"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The country. This attribute is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="o"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The continent. This attribute is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="rl"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The "reading list",
        a list of articles describing visits etc. This can of course
        be empty, i.e., [], but the attribute itself is mandatory. The
        description of what an article object is can be found from
        <xref target="article"/>.</t>

        <t hangText="s"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The source of the data, if specified. The source is simply
        represented as a string.  Note that the source often defaults
        from whereever the data is being fetched, so typically this
        does not need to be set unless somehow specifically different
        from other entries.</t>

        <t hangText="as"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Alternative sources of the data, if more than given in the "s"
        field. This field is optional. If present, it should contain
        an array of strings representing the names of sources.</t>

      </list></t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="article" title="Article Objects">
    
      <t>Aach article is a JSON record. The record has the following fields:
      
      <list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="t"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The title. This attribute is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="i"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        URL for an image representing the article. This attribute is
        optional. If no image URL known, the attribute should not be
        specified at all.</t>
        
        <t hangText="w"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        List of people who were there. This attribute is
        mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="y"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

        Year of visit (as a number). This attribute is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="m"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

        The month of visit (as a number, between 1-12). This attribute
        is mandatory.</t>
        
        <t hangText="a"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

        The activity: Caving, Skiing, etc. This attribute is
        mandatory.</t>

        <t hangText="sa"><vspace blankLines="1"/>

        The sub-activity, e.g., within caving sub-activities or cave
        types are can be Rock, Ice, and so on, wereas within skiing
        they the sub-activities can be Outdoor, Indoor, Snow, Sand,
        and so on. This attribute is mandatory.</t>

        <t hangText="p"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Each article may be described by a URL (if available) or by a
        printed publication such as a book. The "p" field provides the
        name of the book and any associated other reference
        information such as page or section numbers. If there's a URL
        for the book itself (not the article in the book), use the
        field "pu" for that.
        </t>
        
        <t hangText="u"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        URL for the article. This attribute is optional. If no URL is
        known, the attribute should not be specified at all.</t>

        <t hangText="pu"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        URL for a publication that contains the article. E.g., if
        there's an article about the topic or place in a book, place
        the book article here.
        </t>
        
        <t hangText="s"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The source of the data, if specified and different from the
        source of the overall entry.</t>
        
      </list></t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="lc" title="Language Codes">
      <t>The following language codes are supported:
      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="dk">Danish</t>
        <t hangText="fi">Finnish</t>
        <t hangText="fr">French</t>
        <t hangText="de">German</t>
        <t hangText="en">English</t>
        <t hangText="es">Spanish</t>
        <t hangText="it">Italian</t>
        <t hangText="jp">Japanese</t>
        <t hangText="no">Norwegian</t>
        <t hangText="pt">Portuguese</t>
        <t hangText="ru">Russian</t>
        <t hangText="se">Swedish</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      </section>

    </section>
    
    <section anchor="gen1" title="Generation 1 Format">
      
      <t>The format is based on JSON. An Activity JSON Generation 1
      object MUST be a JSON array of records. </t>
      
      <t>For example, an empty file contains just:</t>
      
      <figure>
        <artwork>
          []
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      
      <t>Here's an example of a file with just one entry:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
      [
       {"n": "Kattilajärven iso lippaluola, Nuuksio, Espoo",
        "lat": 60.30145486,
        "lon": 24.62792567,
        "m": "https://example.com/cavemap-kattilajarvi.pdf",
        "l": 9.3,
        "la": "exact",
        "k": "Espoo",
        "c": "Finland",
        "o": "Europe",
        "rl": [{ "t": "Kattilajärvi roof caves",
                 "i": "https://example.com/a-picture.jpg",
                 "w": ["Jari"],
                 "y": 2020,
                 "m": 5,
                 "a": ["Caving"],
                 "sa": ["Rock"],
                 "u": "https://example.com/an-article.html" }
              ]
       }
      ]
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Where the fields are as described in <xref target="prop"/>.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="gen0" title="Generation 0 Format">

      <t>Generation 0 format is similar to Generation 1 format, with the following differences:
      
      <list style="symbols">

      <t>The "k" (city) field was not used.</t>
      <t>The "y" (year) and "m" (month) fields were not used.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="compat" title="Compatibility">
   
      <t>All the formats are very similar. The information content is
      the same, and the attributes about the activities are
      represented literally in the same way. The only differences are
      some additional information in Generation 2 and Generation 1
      formats, and the wrapping of entries in the GeoJSON objects in
      Generation 2 format vs. simply containing them in a list in
      Generations 1 and 2 formats.</t>

      <t>The Psgeo software library supports both <xref
      target="Psgeo"/>, so existing files with content in Generation 1
      format continue to be readable. </t>

      <t>For compatibility between generation 1 and 0, the differences
      are again supported by software libraries and any Generation 0
      content continues to be acceptable by systems consuming Activity
      JSON.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Character Set">
      <t>Activity JSON is always in UTF-8, as specified in <xref
      target="RFC8259"/> Section 8.1.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7946.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8259.xml"?>
      
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="KML">
        <front>
	  <title>OGC KML</title>
          <author initials="T" surname="Wilson"></author>
	  <date month="April" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="OGC 07-147r2" value="version 2.2.20" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Psgeo">
        <front>
	  <title>Psgeo: Activity location library</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Arkko"></author>
	  <date month="May" year="2020" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="website" value="https://github.com/jariarkko/psgeo" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="GeoJSON">
        <front>
	  <title>GeoJSON</title>
          <author><organization>GeoJSON</organization></author>
	  <date month="May" year="2020" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="website" value="https://geojson.org" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="Luolaseura">
        <front>
	  <title>Suomen Luolaseura</title>
          <author><organization>Luolaseura</organization></author>
	  <date month="May" year="2020" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="website" value="https://luolaseura.fi" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="Planetskier">
        <front>
	  <title>Skiing the Planet</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Arkko"></author>
	  <date month="May" year="2020" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="website" value="https://planetskier.net" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="Planetcaver">
	<front>
	  <title>The Planetcaver</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Arkko"></author>
	  <date month="May" year="2020" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="website" value="https://planetcaver.net" />
      </reference>
      
    </references>
    
    <section title="Contributors">
      
      <t>The author would like to acknowledge the contributions of Ralf
      Strandell, Jarmo Ruuth, and Dare Talvitie. Discussions with you
      have greatly enhanced knowledge about this topic.</t>
      
    </section>
    
  </back>
  
</rfc>
